Inventory of the William K. Perrin Papers 1820-1858, 1732-1902
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
William K. Perrin Papers, 1820-1858, 1732-1902.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 95 P42
ca. 200 items.
Business papers, legal papers, and accounts of William K. Perrin and his family, including items concerning the hiring out and management of slaves.
Nicolson family,; Perrin family,; Wyndham Kemp,; Robert W. Nicolson,; Sarah T. Nicolson,; William K. Perrin.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: Acc. No. 1995-18; ca. 200 items, 4/17/1995.
Biographical/Historical Information
William K. Perrin was the son of John and Elizabeth Carter Perrin. In 1833, he married Mrs. Sarah T. Nicolson, daughter of Ralph Wormeley of Middlesex County, Virginia and widow of George D. Nicolson. (Their children were Robert W., George Lewellyn, Andrew T. and James Monroe Nicolson.) The children of William K. Perrin and Sarah T. Nicolson were William Kennon Perrin (1834-1904) and John Tayloe Perrin (b. 1836).
Wyndham Kemp was married to Ann L. Perrin, a daughter of William K. Perrin. She was deceased by 1854. Their children were Perrin Kemp, Wyndham Kemp and Emily Kemp who married Peyton N. Page.
Scope and Content Information
Business letters, 1833-1839, to Major William K. Perrin and 1855, 1860, to his son-in-law Wyndham Kemp, both of Gloucester County, Virginia from Perrin's step-son Robert W. Nicolson in Uniontown, Perry County, Alabama, about the management of a cotton plantation. Letters mention purchasing land, growing and selling cotton management of slaves, legal and banking matters and uprising of the Creek Indians.
Papers, 1800-1855 and n.d., relating to the hiring out and management of slaves of Gloucester County, Virginia by William K. Perrin. Legal papers, 1723-1895, n.d., include indentures, agreements, and lists of debts of William K. Perrin, George D. Nicolson, Sarah T. Nicolson, and descendants of William K. Perrin. Also accounts and receipts, 1806-1902, n.d.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 4 Series. Series 1 contains business papers; Series 2 contains legal papers; Series 3 contains accounts and receipts; Series 4 contains miscellaneous material.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into series which are then arranged chronologically by date.
Additional Descriptive Data
Additional Related Material
There are four collections that relate to the William K. Perrin Papers and are located in Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
John T. Perrin Papers, 1770-1931. 11 boxes. Collection number: Mss. 65 P42
Perrin Family Bibles Collection, ca. 1740-1938. 3 items. Collection number: Mss. 93 P42
James Monroe Nicolson Manuscript Volumes, 1853-1870. 4 items. Collection number: Mss. 76 N52
James Monroe Nicolson Account Books and Papers, 1802-1852. 38 items. Collection number: Mss. 93 N52
Controlled Access Terms
Persons:
Kemp, Wyndham.; Nicolson, Robert W.
Subjects:
Cotton growing.; Slavery-- Alabama.; Creek Indians.; Slavery--Virginia.; Plantations-- Alabama--Perry County.
Geographical Names:
Gloucester County (Va.)--History--19th century.; Perry County (Ala.)--History--19th century.
Components List
  Series 1: Business Papers
- Business papers, 1826-1855. (Folder 1-3)
  - Letters, 1826-1839. (Folder 1)
    A few letters, 1826-1832, to Mrs. Sarah T. Nicolson, Middlesex, including one dated 21 October 1827, stating the decree for dividing "Rosegill" has been set aside; chiefly letters, 1833-1839, to William K. Perrin of "Goshen," Gloucester County, Virginia from his step-son Robert W. Nicolson, Uniontown, Perry County, Alabama about the management of a cotton plantation.
  - Letters, 1844-1884. (Folder 2)
    A few business letters, 1844-1849, to Major William K. Perrin but chiefly letters, 1855-1860, from Robert Nicolson in Alabama to Wyndham Kemp in Gloucester County, Virginia about his cotton crop.
  - Papers relating to the hiring of slaves by William K. Perrin in Gloucester County, Virginia, 1800-1855, n.d. (Folder 3)
    Included are lists of slaves hired out giving names of slaves, masters' names, and amount of transaction, 1800-1806, n.d., receipts for sale of slaves, 1800-1855, and lists of Negroes at Guinea and Fairfield, 1852.
  Series 2: Legal Papers
- Legal Papers, 1723-1895, n.d. (Folder 4-9)
  - Legal papers, 1723-1812. (Folder 4)
    Indentures, lists of accounts for William, Willis, Louisa, and Eliza Perrin in the name of John W. Perrin, guardian, 1800-1807.
  - Legal papers, 1820-1829. (Folder 5)
    Indentures and receipts of William K. Perrin, George D. Nicolson, and Sarah T. Nicolson.
  - Legal papers, 1830-1847. (Folder 6)
    Includes indentures of Sarah T. Nicolson, widow of George D. Nicolson.
  - Legal papers, 1850-1865. (Folder 7)
    Includes agreement, list of debts and receipts of William K. Perrin; last will and testament of William K. Perrin, 16 March 1854 and 25 July 1855; and last will and testament of Willis Perrin, 9 April 1865. Also, Presidential pardon and amnesty granted William K. Perrin for having serves in the Confederate Army, 24 August 1865.
  - Legal papers, 1871-1895. (Folder 8)
    Includes indentures and deeds of the descendants of William K. Perrin.
  - Legal papers, n.d. (Folder 9)
    Miscellaneous items.
  Series 3: Accounts and Receipts
- Accounts and receipts, 1806-1902, n.d. (Box-folder 10-15)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1806-1837. (Folder 10)
    Accounts and receipts of Sarah T. Nicolson, William K. Perrin, and Robert W. Nicolson.
  - Accounts and receipts, 1840-1848. (Folder 11)
    Accounts and receipts of William K. Perrin, Robert W. Nicolson, and Andrew S. Nicolson.
  - Accounts and receipts, 1852-1859. (Folder 12)
    Accounts and receipts of William K. Perrin and Andrew S. Nicolson.
  - Accounts and receipts, 1860-1869. (Folder 13)
    Accounts and receipts of Wyndham Kemp, William K. Perrin, and John T. Perrin.
  - Accounts and receipts, 1870-1902. (Folder 14)
    Accounts and receipts of William K. Perrin.
  - Accounts and receipts, n.d. (Folder 15)
    Miscellaneous accounts of Willis Perrin, and John W. Perrin.
  Series 4: Miscellaneous Material
- Miscellaneous material, n.d. (Box-folder 16-17)
  - The Shorter Catechism. (Folder 16)
  - Envelopes. (Folder 17)